Register of the Polish Information Center (New York, N.Y.) Records
Hoover Institution Archives
Polish Information Center (New York, N.Y.) records
1940-1945
48018
Hoover Institution Archives
82 manuscript boxes, 2 envelopes (32.9 linear feet)
Clippings (primarily from American sources), correspondence, administrative files, press reviews and summaries, bulletins, printed matter, sound recordings, and photographs, relating to World War II, the German and Soviet occupations of Poland, the persecution of Jews in Poland, and the spread of communism in Eastern Europe.
Polish Information Center (New York, N.Y.)
Access
Box 82 closed. The remainder of the collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1948
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (67 reels).
Historical Note
Polish government information and propaganda agency.
Scope and Content Note
The Polish Information Center was founded in 1940 and remained active until 1945. It consisted originally of staff responsible for Poland's presence at the World Fair in New York in 1939; indeed, its first director, Stefan Gotfryd Ropp, was curator of the Polish Pavilion. He remained in his post for the first three years of the center's existence, and was a major force in the creation of a Polish lobby influential in U.S. military, financial, and political circles, particularly to counter American isolationism before the United States entered the war.
Originally called Centrum Informacji Prasowej, the center at first was funded with the proceeds from the sale of objects that couldn't be returned to war torn Poland. In its first year, it operated unofficially, but with the declaration of war by the United States, it had to fulfill certain requirements from the Justice Department. Later, the center became a branch of the Ministry of Information and Documentation. The center's main offices were located on Fifth Avenue, in the heart of New York City, but it eventually had representatives in Chicago, Detroit, Los Angeles, and Pittsburgh.
The center had a well-educated and skilled staff, involved in the collecting and dissemination of information on Poland and on matters relevant to Polish interests in the United States. Ropp himself wrote regular reports for the Polish Ministry of Foreign Affairs, which are excellent examples of his visionary ideas. In the magazine he founded, New Europe, he wrote of a new post war continent, united and free of ideological divisions. This publication was considered one of the most intellectual and most effective instruments of allied propaganda in the United States.
In 1943, the center's structure underwent significant changes and its budget was increased. The broadening of operations found immediate reflection in the way materials were collected: for instance, specialized firms were hired to deliver clippings from hundreds of American newspapers. These clippings constitute three fourths of the collection held at Hoover, and point at issues and events that were of vital interest to the Polish raison d'être. Organized by subject and date, they document developments as they happened, especially for 1943 and 1944 (for other years, the coverage is uneven and in short runs).
The year 1943 was of critical importance to Poland's diplomatic efforts to save its international position after it broke off relations with the Soviet Union and after the death of General Sikorski. Polish politicians found themselves under permanent attack from the American left, which required intensification of their propaganda efforts.
Also in 1943, Ropp was moved to London to head the Biuro Prac Kongresowych responsible for planning the peace conference and a new post-war Poland. Still, the office grew steadily, gradually attracting some of the best minds working for the Polish cause on American soil: from 35 experts in 1943, it employed 51 in 1944.
In 1944, at the peak of its activities, the center had at its disposal a budget of a million dollars. It published weekly bulletins in several languages, as well as numerous brochures on Polish history and politics. During the first six months of the year, over one hundred thousand short publications were distributed, not only in the United States but also in Central America, South Africa, and Australia. Among the recipients of those bulletins and daily reports were the New York Times, Christian Science Monitor, Washington Post, etc. Additionally, some 500-700 letters with inquiries were received and answered each month.
Specialized departments were responsible for the press, radio, exhibits, lectures, films, and cooperation with the United Nations. The Radio Department, for example, delivered programs to numerous English-speaking radio stations, in addition to the 27 Polish-American stations that received regular weekly programs. The center also sponsored the production of some 22 films, and organized several traveling exhibits a year.
Very little in the collection at the Hoover Archives covers the work of those specialized departments operating within the center, such as the German Section (Dzial Niemiecki) directed by Joseph Frejlich, which dealt with the activities of German and German-American circles in the United States. Employees would attend meetings of such groups on the East coast and report back to London. Fortunately, Frejlich also deposited his papers at Hoover, and they should be considered a good complement to the center's records.
The year 1945 brought big budget cuts, and half of the employees were laid off. The center shared the fate of many other Polish diplomatic posts, as the loss of diplomatic recognition of the London government by the Western Allies resulted in the termination of its operations. By decree of Poland's President, Wladyslaw Raczkiewicz, on July 3, 1945, the center was officially shut down.
Its office files were divided among the Pilsudski Institute in New York and the Hoover Institution, which acquired the records described in this register in 1948. Traces of the center's activities can be found in almost all of the other Polish wartime collections at the Hoover Institution in the form of documents, periodicals, and monographs, particularly, as noted above, among the records of the Polish Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Ministry of Information, Ministry of Preparatory Work Concerning the Peace Conference, as well as of the Polish Embassy in Washington.
Holocaust, Jewish (1939-1945); Jews--Poland.; Phonorecords.; Poland--History--Occupation, 1939-1945.; Poland.; Poles in foreign countries.; Polish people--United States.; Propaganda, Polish.; Refugees.; United States--Foreign relations.; World War, 1939-1945--Peace.; World War, 1939-1945--Poland.; World War, 1939-1945--Propaganda.; World War, 1939-1945--Refugees.; World War, 1939-1945.
- Bulletins,., 1941-1946 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Publications issued by the Polish Information Center, arranged alphabetically by title
- Cables,., 1942-1944 (Box 2-3)
  News dispatches in the form of telegrams from London, arranged chronologically
- Clippings,., 1942-1945 (Box 4-61)
  Clippings organized alphabetically by code letters for subjects established by the Center, and therein chronologically
- Correspondence,., 1940-1945 (Box 62-66)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
- Office Files,., 1941-1945 (Box 66-68)
  Budget reports, certificates of employment, newspaper and magazine subscriptions, organizational charts, book and press reviews, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Printed Matter,., 1942-1945 (Box 68)
  Newspaper issues collected by the Center, arranged alphabetically
- Reports,., 1943-1944 (Box 69)
  General note
  Reports submitted to the London authorities, arranged alphabetically by topic or by name of the submitting department
- Subject File,., 1936-1952 (Box 69-81)
  Clippings, leaflets, brochures, arranged alphabetically by subject
- Phonorecords,., 1943 and undated (Box 82)
  Phonorecords of music produced by the Polish government for broadcasting purpose
- Photographs, n.d. (Box Photo file)
  Prints from World War II of Polish refugee children in Great Britain and Africa, and scenes of training troops from Poland and Great Britain
- BULLETINS, 1941-1946 (Box 1)
  - L'Agence télégraphique polonaise PAT: Le bulletin polonais, 1943 July-August (Folder 1: 1)
  - Biuletyn Codzienny PAT, 1943
    - January-April (Folder 1: 2)
    - October (Folder 1: 3)
  - Informacje Ogolne, 1946 June-October (Folder 1: 4)
  - Poland Fights, 1943 October (Folder 1: 5)
  - Polish Feature and News Service, nos. 1-83, 1941-1943 (Folder 1: 6)
- CABLES, 1942-1944 (Box 2)
  - 1942
    - July (Folder 2: 1)
    - August (Folder 2: 2)
    - September (Folder 2: 3)
    - October (Folder 2: 4)
    - November (Folder 2: 5)
    - December (Folder 2: 6)
  - 1943
    - January (Folder 2: 7)
    - February (Folder 2: 8)
    - March (Folder 2: 9)
    - April (Folder 2: 10)
    - May (Folder 2: 11)
    - June (Folder 2: 12)
    - July (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - August (Folder 3: 2)
    - September (Folder 3: 3)
    - October (Folder 3: 4)
    - November (Folder 3: 5)
    - December (Folder 3: 6)
  - 1944
    - January (Folder 3: 7)
    - February (Folder 3: 8)
    - March (Folder 3: 9)
- CLIPPINGS, 1942-1945 (Box 4)
  - General
    - General
      - 1943
        - July (Folder 4: 1)
        - August (Folder 4: 2)
        - December (Folder 4: 3)
      - 1944
        - March (Folder 4: 4)
        - April (Folder 4: 5)
        - May (Folder 4: 6)
        - November (Folder 4: 7)
    - Catholic
      - General. Contains references to the role of the Catholic Church toward Jews
        - General, 1943
          - February (Folder 5: 1)
          - March (Folder 5: 2)
          - April (Folder 5: 3)
        - Church and peace (Folder 5: 4)
        - Church and war (Folder 5: 5)
        - France (Folder 5: 6)
        - Germany
          - General (Folder 5: 7)
          - Nazism (Folder 5: 8)
        - Poland (Folder 5: 9)
        - Post-war reconstruction (Folder 5: 10)
        - Soviet Union - Communism (Folder 5: 11)
      - Czech (Box 6)
        - 1942 December (Folder 6: 1)
        - 1943
          - February (Folder 6: 2)
          - March (Folder 6: 3)
          - April (Folder 6: 4)
      - German
        - 1942 December (Folder 6: 5)
        - 1943
          - February (Folder 6: 6)
          - March (Folder 6: 7)
          - April (Folder 6: 8)
  - A. Poland - Political affairs (Polskie sprawy polityczne) (Box 7)
    - 1943
      - February 16-28 (Folder 7: 1)
      - March
        - 1-15 (Folder 7: 2)
        - 16-31 (Folder 7: 3)
      - April
        - 1-15 (Folder 7: 4)
        - 16-30 (Folder 7: 5)
      - May
        - 1-15 (Folder 7: 6)
        - 16-31
          - General
            - Atlantic region (Folder 7: 7)
            - Midwest region (Folder 7: 8)
            - Pacific region (Folder 7: 9)
          - Jewish (Folder 7: 10)
      - June 15-30
        - General
          - General (Folder 7: 11)
          - Atlantic (Folder 7: 12)
          - Midwest (Folder 7: 13)
        - Jewish (Folder 7: 14)
      - July
        - 1-15
          - General
            - Atlantic (Folder 7: 15)
            - Midwest (Folder 7: 16)
          - Jewish (Folder 7: 17)
        - 16-31
          - General
            - Atlantic (Folder 7: 18)
            - Midwest (Folder 7: 19)
            - Pacific (Folder 7: 20)
          - Jewish (Folder 7: 21)
      - August
        - 1-15 (Folder 7: 22)
        - 16-31 (Folder 7: 23)
      - September (Folder 7: 24)
      - October (Folder 7: 25)
      - November (Folder 7: 26)
    - 1944
      - August
        - Polish Army in Italy (Folder 7: 27)
        - Warsaw Uprising (Folder 7: 28)
      - - Warsaw Uprising, September (Folder 7: 29)
      - October
        - General (Folder 7: 30)
        - Warsaw Uprising (Folder 7: 31)
  - B. Poland - Political affairs (Polskie sprawy polityczne) (Box 8)
    - 1942
      - General (Folder 8: 1)
      - Jewish (Folder 8: 2)
    - 1943
      - January
        - 1-15
          - General (Folder 8: 3)
          - Jewish (Folder 8: 4)
        - 16-31
          - General (Folder 8: 5)
          - Jewish (Folder 8: 6)
      - February
        - General
          - Atlantic (Folder 8: 7)
          - Midwest (Folder 8: 8)
        - Jewish
          - 1-15 (Folder 8: 9)
          - 16-28 (Folder 8: 10)
      - March
        - 1-15
          - General
            - Atlantic (Folder 8: 11)
            - Midwest (Folder 8: 12)
            - Pacific (Folder 9: 1)
          - Jewish (Folder 9: 2)
        - 16-31
          - General
            - Atlantic (Folder 9: 3)
            - Midwest (Folder 9: 4)
            - Pacific (Folder 9: 5)
          - Jewish (Folder 9: 6)
      - April
        - 1-15
          - General
            - Atlantic (Folder 9: 7)
            - Midwest (Folder 9: 8)
          - Jewish (Folder 9: 9)
        - 16-30
          - General
            - Atlantic (Folder 9: 10)
            - Midwest (Folder 9: 11)
            - Pacific (Folder 9: 12)
          - Jewish (Folder 9: 13)
      - May (Box 10)
        - 1-15
          - General
            - Atlantic (Folder 10: 1)
            - Midwest (Folder 10: 2)
            - Pacific (Folder 10: 3)
          - Jewish (Folder 10: 4)
        - 16-31
          - Atlantic (Folder 10: 5)
          - Midwest (Folder 10: 6)
          - Pacific (Folder 10: 7)
      - June
        - 1-15
          - Atlantic (Folder 10: 8)
          - Midwest (Folder 10: 9)
          - Pacific (Folder 10: 10)
        - 16-30
          - General
            - Atlantic (Folder 10: 11)
            - Midwest (Folder 10: 12)
            - Pacific (Folder 10: 13)
          - Jewish (Folder 10: 14)
      - July
        - 1-15
          - General
            - Atlantic (Folder 11: 1)
            - Midwest (Folder 11: 2)
            - Pacific (Folder 11: 3)
          - Jewish press (Folder 11: 4)
          - Sikorski's death (Folder 11: 5)
        - 16-31
          - General
            - Atlantic (Folder 11: 6)
            - Midwest (Folder 11: 7)
          - Jewish press (Folder 11: 8)
      - August (Box 12)
        - 1-15
          - General
            - Atlantic (Folder 12: 1)
            - Midwest (Folder 12: 2)
          - Jewish (Folder 12: 3)
        - 16-31
          - General
            - Atlantic (Folder 12: 4)
            - Midwest (Folder 12: 5)
            - Pacific (Folder 12: 6)
          - Jewish (Folder 12: 7)
      - September
        - 1-15
          - General
            - General (Folder 12: 8)
            - Atlantic (Folder 12: 9)
          - Jewish (Folder 12: 10)
        - 15-30
          - General
            - Atlantic (Folder 12: 11)
            - Midwest (Folder 12: 12)
            - Pacific (Folder 12: 13)
          - Jewish (Folder 12: 14)
      - October (Box 13)
        - General
          - General (Folder 13: 1)
          - Atlantic (Folder 13: 2)
          - Midwest (Folder 13: 3)
          - Pacific (Folder 13: 4)
        - Jewish (Folder 13: 5)
      - November
        - General
          - 1-15 (Folder 13: 6)
          - 16-30 (Folder 13: 7)
        - Polish (Folder 13: 8)
      - December (Folder 13: 9)
    - 1944
      - March (Folder 13: 10)
      - October (Folder 13: 11)
        - November (Folder 13: 12)
  - C. Poland - Economic affairs (Polskie sprawy ekonomiczne)
    - 1942 November-December (Folder 13: 13)
    - 1943
      - March-August (Folder 13: 14)
      - September-October (Folder 13: 15)
  - D. Poland - Various affairs (Polskie sprawy rozne) (Box 14)
    - 1943
      - May 16-31
        - General (Folder 14: 1)
        - Jewish (Folder 14: 2)
      - June
        - 1-15 (Folder 14: 3)
        - 16-30 (Folder 14: 4)
      - July
        - 1-15 (Folder 14: 5)
        - 16-31 (Folder 14: 6)
      - August
        - 1-15 (Folder 14: 7)
        - 16-31 (Folder 14: 8-9)
      - September (Box-folder 15: 1-3)
      - October-November (Folder 15: 4)
    - 1944-November (Folder 15: 5)
  - E. Russia (Rosja)
    - 1942 November-December
      - Atlantic (Folder 15: 6)
      - Midwest (Folder 15: 7)
    - 1943
      - January
        - 1-15
          - Atlantic (Folder 15: 8-9)
          - Midwest (Folder 15: 10)
        - 16-31
          - Atlantic (Folder 15: 11)
          - Midwest (Box-folder 16: 1)
          - Pacific (Folder 16: 2)
      - February
        - 1-15
          - Atlantic (Folder 16: 3)
          - Midwest (Folder 16: 4)
          - Pacific (Folder 16: 5)
        - - Atlantic, 16-28 (Folder 16: 6)
      - March
        - 1-15
          - General
            - Atlantic (Folder 16: 7)
            - Midwest (Folder 17: 1)
            - Pacific (Folder 17: 2)
          - Jewish (Folder 17: 3)
        - 16-31
          - General
            - Atlantic (Folder 17: 4)
            - Midwest (Folder 17: 5)
            - Pacific (Folder 17: 6)
          - Jewish (Folder 17: 7)
      - April
        - - Atlantic, 1-15 (Folder 17: 8)
        - 16-30
          - General
            - Atlantic (Folder 17: 9)
            - Midwest (Folder 17: 10)
            - Pacific (Folder 17: 11)
          - Jewish (Folder 17: 12)
      - May
        - General
          - Atlantic
            - 1-15 (Folder 17: 13)
            - 16-23 (Folder 17: 14)
            - 24-31 (Box-folder 18: 1)
          - Midwest, 16-31 (Folder 18: 2)
          - Pacific, 16-31 (Folder 18: 3)
        - Jewish, 16-31 (Folder 18: 4)
      - June
        - 1-15
          - General
            - Atlantic (Folder 18: 5)
            - Midwest (Folder 18: 6)
            - Pacific (Folder 18: 7)
          - Jewish (Folder 18: 8)
        - 16-30 (Box 19)
          - General
            - Atlantic (Folder 19: 1)
            - Midwest (Folder 19: 2)
            - Pacific (Folder 19: 3)
          - Jewish (Folder 19: 4)
      - July
        - 1-15
          - General
            - Atlantic (Folder 19: 5)
            - Midwest (Folder 19: 6)
            - Pacific (Folder 19: 7)
          - Jewish (Folder 19: 8)
        - 16-31
          - General
            - Atlantic (Folder 19: 9)
            - Midwest (Folder 19: 10)
            - Pacific (Folder 19: 11)
          - Jewish (Box-folder 20: 1)
      - August
        - 1-15
          - General
            - Atlantic (Folder 20: 2-3)
            - Midwest (Folder 20: 4)
            - Pacific (Folder 20: 5)
          - Jewish (Folder 20: 6)
        - 16-31
          - General
            - Atlantic (Folder 20: 7-8)
            - Midwest (Box-folder 21: 1)
            - Pacific (Folder 21: 2)
          - Jewish (Folder 21: 3)
      - September
        - 1-15
          - General
            - Atlantic (Folder 21: 4)
            - Midwest (Folder 21: 5)
            - Pacific (Folder 21: 6)
          - Jewish (Folder 21: 7)
        - 16-30 (Box 22)
          - General
            - Atlantic
              - 16-21 (Folder 22: 1)
              - 22-24 (Folder 22: 2)
              - 25-27 (Folder 22: 3)
              - 28-30 (Folder 22: 4)
            - Midwest (Folder 22: 5)
            - Pacific (Folder 22: 6)
          - Jewish (Folder 22: 7)
      - October (Box 23)
        - 1-3 (Folder 23: 1)
        - 4-6 (Folder 23: 2)
        - 7-9 (Folder 23: 3)
        - 10-12 (Folder 23: 4)
        - 13-15 (Folder 23: 5)
        - 16-20 (Box-folder 24: 1)
        - 21-24 (Folder 24: 2)
        - 25-31 (Folder 24: 3-4)
      - November
        - 1-2 (Folder 25: 1)
        - 3-5 (Folder 25: 2)
        - 6-10 (Folder 25: 3)
        - 11-14 (Folder 25: 4)
        - 15-17 (Folder 25: 5)
        - 18-20 (Folder 25: 6)
        - 21-24 (Box-folder 26: 1)
        - 25-30 (Folder 26: 2)
      - December
        - 1 (Folder 26: 3)
        - 2-6 (Folder 26: 4)
        - 7-9 (Folder 26: 5)
        - 10-14 (Folder 26: 6)
        - 16-31 (Folder 26: 7)
    - 1944 (Box 27)
      - January
        - 1-15
          - American
            - Atlantic
              - 1-5 (Folder 27: 1)
              - 6-9 (Folder 27: 2)
              - 10-15 (Folder 27: 3-4)
            - Midwest (Box-folder 28: 1)
            - Pacific (Folder 28: 2)
          - Canadian (Folder 28: 3)
          - Jewish (Folder 28: 4)
        - 16-19 (Folder 28: 5)
        - 20-25 (Folder 28: 6)
        - 26-31 (Folder 28: 7)
      - February (Folder 28: 8)
      - March (Folder 28: 9)
      - April (Box 29)
      - May
        - 1-15 (Folder 29: 1)
        - 16-31 (Folder 29: 2)
      - June
        - 1-15 (Folder 29: 3)
        - 16-30 (Folder 29: 4)
      - August (Folder 29: 5)
      - September (Folder 29: 6)
      - November (Folder 29: 7)
  - F. Germany (Niemcy) (Box 30)
    - 1942
      - November (Folder 30: 1)
      - December (Folder 30: 2)
    - 1943
      - January
        - 1-15 (Folder 30: 3)
        - 16-31 (Folder 30: 4)
      - February
        - 1-15 (Folder 30: 5)
        - 16-28 (Folder 30: 6)
      - March
        - ., 1-15 (Folder 30: 7)
          Includes reports on Germans in the United States
        - 16-31 (Folder 30: 8)
      - April (Box 31)
        - 1-15 (Folder 31: 1)
        - 16-30 (Folder 31: 2)
      - May
        - 1-15 (Folder 31: 3)
        - 16-31
          - Atlantic (Folder 31: 4)
          - Midwest (Folder 31: 5)
          - Pacific (Folder 31: 6)
      - June
        - 1-15
          - General
            - Atlantic (Folder 31: 7)
            - Midwest (Folder 31: 8)
            - Pacific (Folder 31: 9)
          - Jewish (Folder 31: 10)
        - 16-30
          - General
            - Atlantic (Folder 31: 11)
            - Midwest (Folder 31: 12)
            - Pacific (Folder 31: 13)
          - Jewish (Folder 31: 14)
      - July (Box 32)
        - 1-15
          - Atlantic (Folder 32: 1)
          - Midwest (Folder 32: 2)
          - Pacific (Folder 32: 3)
        - 16-31
          - General
            - Atlantic (Folder 32: 4)
            - Midwest (Folder 32: 5)
            - Pacific (Folder 32: 6)
          - Jewish (Folder 32: 7)
      - August
        - 1-15
          - General
            - Atlantic (Folder 32: 8)
            - Midwest (Folder 32: 9)
            - Pacific (Folder 32: 10)
          - Jewish (Folder 32: 11)
        - 16-31
          - Atlantic (Folder 32: 12)
          - Midwest (Folder 32: 13)
          - Pacific (Folder 32: 14)
      - September 1-15 (Folder 32: 15)
      - October
        - 1-15 (Folder 32: 16)
        - 16-30
          - Atlantic (Folder 32: 17)
          - Jewish (Folder 32: 18)
      - November (Folder 32: 19)
  - G. Atlantic Charter, Four Freedoms, Lend-Lease (Karta Atlantycka, Four Freedoms, Lend-Lease) (Box 33)
    - 1942 November-December (Folder 33: 1)
    - 1943
      - January
        - 1-15 (Folder 33: 2)
        - 16-31 (Folder 33: 3)
      - February
        - 1-15 (Folder 33: 4)
        - 16-28 (Folder 33: 5)
      - March
        - 1-15 (Folder 33: 6)
        - 16-31 (Folder 33: 7)
      - April
        - 1-15 (Folder 33: 8)
        - 16-30 (Folder 33: 9)
      - May
        - 1-15 (Folder 33: 10)
        - 16-31
          - Atlantic (Folder 33: 11)
          - Midwest (Folder 33: 12)
          - Pacific (Folder 33: 13)